Guide to the Rice University scrapbook collection, 1907-1985 UA 230
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University scrapbook collection
1907-1985
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University
UA 230
62.5 Linear Feet (46 boxes)
6.86 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0230aip_001 (6.86 GB)
The collections includes a series of scrapbooks of the activities of Rice alumni and a series of scrapbooks from Rice University departments, Rice-related events, and other materials related to the life of the university.
Historical Note
Records of the activities of Rice University students have been captured in scrapbooks by alumni since the opening of the Institute in 1912. The scrapbooks in the collection contain ephemera reflecting the stimulating life on campus, including photographs, correspondence, invitations, newsclippings, tickets, etc, related to academic, social, sports, and arts events and organizations. The materials in these scrapbooks help document the change in the community as Rice grew from the Institute out on the prairie to a world class university surrounded by a major metropolitan area. The collection also includes scrapbooks of the Treasurer's Office beginning in 1907 as the Institute was being planned and scrapbooks from various other Rice departments and Rice-related events.
Scope and Contents
The collections includes a series of scrapbooks of the activities of Rice alumni and a series of scrapbooks from Rice University departments, Rice-related events, and other materials related to the life of the university. Additional scrapbooks, such as the scrapbooks created by the Literary Societies, can be found in the related record groups.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Portions of this collection are available online at: https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/95187
Acquisition Information
These records have been donated to the Woodson Research Center by multiple individuals and departments over a number of years.
Index Terms
Subjects
Social life and customs; Universities and colleges; Women
Document Types
photographs; clippings (information artifacts); invitations; corrrespondence
Subjects (Corporations)
Rice University; Rice University
- Series I: Rice Alumni Scrapbooks, 1912 - 1970; 130555
  General
  This series contains scrapbooks of the activities of Rice alumni, including photographs, invitations, newsclippings and other ephemera.
  - Ray Watkin Hoagland, 1936; 130560 (Box 1, Item 1)
    Ray Watkin Hoagland graduated from Rice Institute in 1936 with a B.A. in French. She actively served as a senior member of the Honor Council; a member of Pi Delta Phi, the honorary French society; a member of the French Alliance in Houston; and a member of Phi Beta Kappa, the honorary scholastic society. She was also a society girl who was selected as a Duchess of the Mardi Gras Court in Galveston, a Queen of the Archi-Arts Ball, and a Princess of the May Fete. The many invitations and thank-you letters placed neatly throughout her scrapbook are indicative of her popularity and social status.
  - Hannah Rembert Fogler, 1938; 130578 (Box 1, Item 2)
    Hannah Rembert Fogler graduated from Rice Institute in 1938. She was a fan of Rice football and tracked both the games and the players devotedly. Her scrapbook features news clippings, comic strips, and portraits related to Rice football.
  - Anah Marie Leland, 1919 - 1921; 130633 (Box 2, Item 1)
    Anah Marie Leland graduated from Rice Institute in 1922 with a B.A. in philosophy. She enjoyed both watching and acting in theatre as well as attending dances. She was considered a society girl and filled her scrapbook with programs, ticket stubs, invitations, party photographs, and more. Leland became engaged to James Lockhart Autry III while at Rice and features him in her scrapbook, but Autry died in 1922 shortly before the wedding. Later she became involved with Autry's best friend, W.M. Streetman, and married him.
  - Charles Sedwick Matthews, 1941; 130635 (Box 2, Item 2)
    Charles Sedwick Matthews graduated from Rice Institute in 1941 with B.S. in chemical engineering. He won the first annual Phi Lambda Upsilon award from the National Honorary Chemistry Society and the Graham Baker Studentship award, both because he had the highest scholastic ranking. Matthews also served as President of his senior class. While subsequently pursuing his Ph.D., he was offered jobs for when he graduated at the Humble Oil & Refining Company and The Texas Company.
  - Mary Carolyn Dearmond, 1958; 130640 (Box 3, Item 1)
    Mary Carolyn Dearmond graduated from Rice Institute in 1958 with a B.A. in English amd was awarded the Lady Washington Texas Centenntial Award. She was an intramural swimmer at Rice and taught a swimming class for children and adults in her spare time. She was also a fan of football and Rice's only girl cheerleader. Scattered throughout her scrapbook are photos and letters related to Tom Lubbock, who seems to have been her significant other living in California.
  - Dorothy Weiser Seale, 1937; 130644 (Box 4, Item 1)
    Dorothy Weiser Seale, the daughter of Dean H. B. Weiser, graduated from Rice Institute in 1937. During her time at Rice, Seale was May Queen, vice president of the Student Association, Archi-Arts beauty, Galveston Mardi Gras Princess, a participant of the Thresher and Owl yearbook staff, president of the Writing Club, and secretary of Pallas Athene Literary Society. She was even selected as one of Rice Institute's "Most Beautiful Girls." Three years after graduation, Dorothy Weiser Seale was the first bride to wed at Cohen House, home of the Rice Faculty Club, and has since returned the precious silver bowl, given to her as a wedding present by Agnes Cohen, to Rice University as a historical keepsake.
  - William T. Matlage, 1938; 130646 (Box 4, Item 2)
    William T. Matlage, M.D., graduated from Rice Institute in 1936 with a B.A. He was an avid fan of Rice football and basketball, collecting many newspaper clippings and comic strips on the subject. He was also a musician in the Rice Owl Band and an attendee of a variety of Rice balls and dances. After graduation he studied medicine at Galveston.
  - Katherine Otilla Thompson, 1927; 130650 (Box 4, Item 3)
    Katherine Otilla Thompson graduated from Rice Institute in 1927 with a bachelor's degree. In her scrapbook she included a story that she had written for a creative writing class at Rice.
  - Mary McCarty Symns, 1919; 130654 (Box 5, Item 1)
    Mary McCarty Symms graduated from Rice Institute in 1919. Her scrapbooks primarily consist of newspaper clippings from a variety of Rice-related events that do not necessarily feature her, such as the school's societies, elections, dances, clubs, and more.
  - Edith Ellen Howze, 1929; 130655 (Box 5, Item 2)
    Previously a Houston Central High School student, Edith Ellen Howze graduated from Rice Institute in 1929. She was interested in fashion and style and was voted one of Rice's seven most beautiful girls. She also hosted and attended teas with other high social ladies. She enjoyed following the events of Rice football, classes, and freshmen "Slime" initiation.
  - Elliot Flowers, 1934; 130656 (Box 5, Item 3)
    Elliot Flowers graduated from Rice Institute in 1934. He was Assistant Editor of The Rice Owl and a member of the Rice Institute Athletic Association. He enjoyed attending many dances, football games, and shows by the Rice Dramatic Club.
  - Margaret Waples, 1916; 130667 (Box 6, Item 1)
    Margaret Waples graduated from Rice Institute in 1916. Her scrapbook consists of black and white photographs of Rice's campus, her peers, the Y.W.C.A., and her professors.
  - Gladys Patterson Wilkins, 1919; 130672 (Box 6, Item 2)
    Gladys Patterson Wilkins graduated from Rice Institute in 1919. Her scrapbook consists of black and white photographs from her experience at Rice, ranging from commencement to the Y.W.C.A Picnic to snapshots around campus.
  - Maxwell O. Read, 1940; 130675 (Box 6, Item 3)
    Maxwell O. Reade graduated from Rice Institute in 1940 with a Ph.D. in mathematics. His scrapbook consists primarily of black and white photographs of his experiences at Rice, from football games to the Faculty Tower to friendly Fellows in Math. Neat captions explain the contents of each picture.
  - Annette Gano Gragg, 1947; 130683 (Box 6, Item 4)
    Annette Gano Gragg graduated from Rice Institute in 1947 with a B.S. in architecture. In her scrapbook she includes schedules, required texts, and required supplies for her architecture classes. She was also an Archi-Arts Ball honoree, who was then elected queen, and a member of the Elizabeth Baldwin Literary Society (EBLS). She enjoyed attending Rice dances and hosting EBLS teas.
  - Barry Talbot, 1932; 130684 (Box 6, Item 5)
    Barry Talbot graduated from Rice Institute in 1932. Talbot was a senior class representative of the Student Council, a member of the Junior Prom Committee, and a Rice Chronicle correspondent. He was also a member of the Thresher staff, Campanile staff, R and Quill Association, and Writing Club. Consequently, in his scrapbook he collected many newspaper clippings of a wide variety of Rice-related events, such as society and club meetings, visiting guest speakers, sports, the May Fete, and more.
    Scope and Contents
  - Mary Jane Stratford Torrens, 1918; 130685 (Box 6, Item 6)
    Mary Jane Stratford Torrens graduated from Rice Institute in 1918. She was the daughter of Rice's first Dean of Women Students. She was held the official role of Critic in the Elizabeth Baldwin Literary Society and was a member of the Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA).
  - Mary Frances Campbell, 1934 - 1935; 130686 (Box 7, Item 1)
    Mary Frances Campbell graduated from Rice Institute in 1938. She was a member of the Owen Wister Literary Society and enjoyed following Rice football and theatre. In "A Toast to the Ladies," she was voted repeatedly for having the most beautiful face. She was also a freshman maid at the May Fete. During her time at Rice, she experienced facial and head injuries in a car crash with her peers.
  - Doris Sue Moellenbernt, 1948; 130687 (Box 8, Item 1)
    Doris Sue Moellenbernt graduated from Rice Institute in 1948. She was the president of the Sarah Lane Literary Society and an officer for its publicity committee. Moellenbernt often hosted parties for the society. She was judged the best feminine role in the play "Trysting Place" performed by the Rice Dramatics Club. She was also one of the models from Rice in a style show, "Diane's Diary," presented by the Triniy Women's association. At the Archi-Arts Ball with an "Alice in Wonderland" theme, she was nominated as Titania, "Who Drank the Love Potion," for the pageant. In 1949 she became engaged to Dr. Karl C. tenBrink, a fellow Rice graduate.
  - Neil Brennan, n.d.; 130688 (Box 8, Item 2)
    Brennan seems to have been a writer for the newspaper. His scrapbook pages include many photos of the Rice Institute campus.
  - Carl Knapp, 1916; 130715 (Box 9, Item 1)
    Carl Knapp graduated from Rice Institute in 1916. He later becamethe president of the Rice Alumni Club. His scrapbook includes many photos of Rice students and professors, especially related to athletics and the engineering department.
  - William Max Nathan, 1912 - 1916; 130716 (Box 9, Item 2)
    William Max Nathan graduated from Rice Institute in 1916. He was the business manager of The Campanile and a member of the Young Men's Christian Association. During his time at Rice, he had a conflict with the reorganization and politics of the Goethe Verein, of which he previously had been a member. His scrapbook includes many photographs of the buildings and people at Rice. He also included many materials from his classes and events.
  - Carl Knapp addendum (Box 9a)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Brought in by Carl Knapp's daughters in 2012 for the Rice History Corner blog post. There is no deed of gift, since the daughter is now deceased.
  - Elmer Shutts, 1916; 130717 (Box 10, Item 1)
    Elmer Shutts graduated from Rice Institute in 1916 with a B.S. in Engineering. Shutts was the Rice baseball manager, "the guy who handles the money." His scrapbook includes many black and white photographs of the Rice campus, his peers, his future wife Lillie Mae Ford, and the baseball team.
  - Fred Manaker, 1918; 130718 (Box 10, Item 2)
    Fred Manaker graduated from Rice Institute in 1918 with a B.S. in Electrical Engineering. He enjoyed watching Rice sports, especially football, and he loved flying his airplane, even using it to take probably the first aerial photographs of Rice. After graduation, he served as Second Lieutenant, Air Service (Aeronautics), for the U.S. military. Unfortunately Manaker died in a plane crash on his way home to visit family and friends. His scrapbook contains photographs, letters, and newsclippings regarding his service in the air force and his crash.
  - Milo W. Ford, Jr., 1940; 130719 (Box 11, Item 1)
    Milo W. Ford, Jr., graduated from Rice Institute in 1940. He was interested in Rice football, freshmen hazing, and women at Rice. Because he worked at the Houston Museum of Fine Arts while attending Rice, his scrapbook includes many newspaper articles related to and ephemera from the museum.
  - Allie May Autry, 1925; 130724 (Box 12, Item 1)
    Allie May Autry graduated from Rice Institute in 1925. As a freshman, she was elected vice president of her class and led the grand march at the Freshman Dance with President Asbury. Autry enjoyed attending dances, winning the costume prize at the Sophomore Kid dance and leading the grand march at junior prom. She was also a member of the Tattlers Club and the Students Association. Her brother and fellow Rice graduate, James L. Autry, unfortunately died at the age of 24 right before his marriage, and her scrapbook recollects this tragedy.
  - Jessie H. Sloan, 1920s; 130725 (Box 12, Item 2)
    Jessie H. Sloan graduated from Rice Institute in 1924. Her scrapbook includes black and white photographs of the Rice campus, her peers, and her graduation.
  - John "Jack" Blythe Halton Henderson, 1925-1927 (Box 12, Item 3)
    These scrapbook pages contain images of Henderson's time at the Rice Institute, engineering field trips, and work life in and around the Houston Ship Channel. The folder also contains an obituary and other biographical information about Henderson. Includes an autographed photograph of Adriaan Paulen.
  - Emmett Brunson, 1927 - 1940s; 130743 (Box 13, Item 1)
    Emmett Brunson graduated from Rice Institute in the late 1920s. He was a Rice track star, competing in the NCAA championships, and became a member of the Rice Athletic Hall of Fame. In one competition he had the distinction of winning first place in all events he entered. Lawson Robertson, head coach of the U.S. Olympic track team, even invited Brunson to train with him in 1928. Soon Brunson became a track coach at Rice in 1934 and was selected for the American Olympic Track and Field Committee in 1938.
  - Track Scrapbook, 1940 - 1970; 130752 (Box 13, Item 2)
    This scrapbook consists primarily of newspaper clippings and photographs related to Rice Institute's track and field team from about 1940 to 1970. The articles cover team victories, player profiles, competitions, and scores. The scrapbook was owned by Emmett Brunson, a famous Rice track star, coach, and Olympian committee member.
  - Reginald Bickford, 1923; 130753 (Box 14, Item 1)
    Reginald Bickford graduated from Rice Institute in 1923. However, his scrapbook consists of materials from around 1948. Many of his newspaper clippings are related to architectural developments at Rice, and his photographs depict peers and athletics. Bickford was the president of the Chicago Rice Alumni Club and a member of the Idlers Club.
  - Wash Underwood, 1925 - 1926; 130754 (Box 14, Item 2)
    Wash "Heavy" Underwood graduated from Rice Institute in 1926. He was a star football player and team captain at Rice. He was known for his versatility on the field, excelling in any position he was placed in. Underwood primarily played center and was considered the best punter on the team. He was nicknamed "Heavy" not only because of his bulk--weighing about 200 lbs--but also because his older brother, who was also a Rice star, was known by the same title. Underwood was awarded the most valuable player trophy offered annually by the College inn in 1926 and was runner-up for the varsity award, the highest honor that a Rice football player can receive.
  - Walter W. Trout, 1918; 130755 (Box 14, Item 3)
    Walter W. Trout graduated from Rice Institute in 1921. He seems to have been a member of the Student Army Training Corps (SATC). He attended dances and football games.
  - Ervin A. Kalb, 1913 - 1915; 130756 (Box 15, Item 1)
    Ervin A. Kalb graduated from Rice Institute in 1916. Kalb was a member of the Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA), giving speeches at their banquets and buying stock in their facility, Camp Sandyhook. Kalb was also the captain of the basket ball team, playing center, and the team's president. In addition, he was a member of the track and field team in 1914, participating in discus throw and shot put. In 1916 Kalb was elected editor in chief for the first annual or year book to be published by a senior class at Rice Institute, and this book became known as the Campanile. Apparently his disorderly conduct in the dining room at Rice led to his suspension from the Residential Hall for Men for one week by the Hall Committee. He also had low grades and attendance, which resulted in him being called upon by the Committee on Examination and Standing, and the committee informed him he must make up several classes.
  - ZueBelle Shaw, 1934; 130757 (Box 15, Item 2)
    Zue Belle Shaw graduated from Rice Institute in 1934. Shaw was a member of the Elizabeth Baldwin Literary Society, Junior Prom Committee, Young Women's Christian Association and Glee Club. She enjoyed following Rice football, filling her scrapbook entirely with newspaper articles and photographs related to the football team. She even included a page with what seems to be the football players' autographs.
  - Larry Hamilton, 1929; 130758 (Box 15, Item 3)
    Larry Hamilton graduated from Rice Institute in 1929. Hamilton was an honors student and a member and letterman of the Rice track and field team, who were Southwestern Conference champions during his time. He competed in the 220-yard hurdles and the one mile team relay race. Hamilton was also the business manager of the Campanile in 1929 and the president of the "R" association of Rice lettermen. His scrapbook includes track-related newspaper articles and photographs, conference programs, and track numbers worn by Hamilton himself. In addition, his scrapbook includes portraits of his fellow members of the Campanile. After graduation, he remained an active supporter of Rice sports, recruiting West Coast student-athletes for the university, and established a golfing scholarship in his name. In 1989 he was named one of Rice's "Distinguished 'R' Men" of the year.
  - Louise Moore, 1922; 130759 (Box 16, Item 1)
    Louise Moore graduated from Rice Institute in 1922. Moore was a member of the Tattler's Club and a member of the advisory committee on the editorial staff for the Owl Calendar. She was also a Rice representative at a students' volunteer conference, the vice president of her sophomore class, an officer of Student Council, and a sophomore maid at the May Fete. As a junior she served on the refreshment committee for the prom. During her education she spent time in New York studying music, specifically voice culture, with Frank LaForge, and a bridge-musical-tea was hosted in her honor. She enjoyed collecting humorous quotes or poems from The Thresher as well as Rice dance- and sport-related ephemera in her scrapbook.
  - Adele Waggaman, 1917; 130760 (Box 16, Item 2)
    Adele Waggaman graduated from Rice Institute in 1917. She was a member and officer of the Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA) and a member of the German Club. She also took a photograph of Rice's first football team. Many of her personal photographs depict her peers being frivolous and having fun, such as at YWCA parties and the style shows at the junior minstrels.
  - Juanita Ross, 1940 - 1943; 130761 (Box 17, Item 1)
    Juanita Ross graduated from Rice Institute in 1943 with a B.A. She enjoyed following Rice football, collecting Christmas cards, and attending the Delman Theatre. She was chosen to be one of the Thomas R. Franklin and Julia H. Franklin Scholars in 1942 and initiated into the Rice chapter of Sigma XI, honorary scientific society. While a student, she was also a teacher's assistant, earning much of her college expenses back. She was also a member of the 4-H Club, extension service county agent work related to Texas A&M. Ross was certified by the American National Red Cross for completing the standard course in Red Cross Home Nursing. Because the U.S. was being affected by the international affairs of Nazi Germany, Rice Institute's resources were more limited, resulting in the delay of the May Fete and other events during Ross's time there. After graduation, she accepted a position in the chemistry department of the Humble Oil & Refining Co.
  - Anna Gilliland Schirmer Vilbig, 1918; 130762 (Box 18, Item 1)
    Anna Gilliland Schirmer Vilbirg graduated from Rice Institute in 1920. She was a member of the Idler's Club, the Tattler's Club, the Students' Association, the Young Women's Christian Association, the Elizabeth Baldwin Literary Society, and the Rho Iota, a girls' club to promote friendship. She was elected secretary of the sophomore class and was awarded a scholarship in civics and philanthropy in 1919-1920. She was also featured in the newspaper as one of the very attractive and popular co-eds of Rice Institute who was invited to many parties. She married to J. Lee Vilberg, Jr., a fellow Rice graduate who served in the military.
  - Carolyn Dearmond, 1956; 130763 (Box 18, Item 2)
    Carolyn Dearmond graduated from Rice Institute in 1958 with a B.A. in English and the aspiration to teach. Dearmond competed for Miss Football honors on behalf of Rice Institute at the Berkeley football festival, during which she also attended Disneyland and collected festive ephemera. Because of the contest, she met Clint Walker, a star of the Warner Bros. TV show "Cheyenne." She was also a Rice's only female cheerleader at the time.
  - John E. Niland, 1917; 130764 (Box 19, Item 1)
    John E. Niland graduated from Rice Institute in 1917. He attended a variety of musical performances and sport events. He has some strange items in his scrapbook, including a pair of socks.
  - Roy A. Taylor, 1917 - 1921?; 130799 (Box 20, Item 1)
    Roy A. Taylor graduated from Rice Institute around 1921. He seems to have been a member of the SATC.
  - Albert Tomforde, 1913 - 1917?; 130800 (Box 20, Item 2)
    Albert Tomforde graduated from Rice Institute in 1918. Tomforde was a member of the Idler's Club and enjoyed attending Rice athletic events. He was also a winner of the "R" in Rice's "R" Association. He had a membership with Monta Beach's School for Dancing and apparently could read German.
  - Mary LeGrande Shacklett, 1919 - 1923; 130801 (Box 21, Item 1)
    Mary LeGrande Shacklett graduated from Rice Institute in 1923. Shacklett enjoyed attending Rice dances and following local weddings. She was also a maid of honor at the 1922 May Fete and the Duchess of the House of Senior at the 1923 May Fete. Shacklett was a member of the Students' Association and the Athletic Association.
  - Mary Jane Hale Rommel, 1930s; 130802 (Box 21, Item 2)